Guide to the James T. Watkins Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
James T. Watkins papers
1939-1979
SC0209
Watkins, James T. (James Thomas), 1907-1982.
30 Linear feet
Contents include correspondence, class materials, and files relating to university and political science department activities as well as to Stanford sports.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of Professor James T. Watkins, IV, 1979.
Information about Access
Materials in boxes 1-2 are restricted 75 years from date of creation.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Watkins received his A.B. (1929), A.M. (1934) and PhD. (1941) from Stanford; Professor of Political Science at Stanford (1946-1973; emeritus, 1973-1982).
Description of the Collection
Contents include correspondence, class materials, and files relating to university and political science department activities as well as to Stanford sports.
Access Terms
Stanford University. Department of Political Science.; Watkins, James T. (James Thomas), 1907-1982.; Athletics; Stanford University--Student housing.
Collection Contents
- Papers, 1939-1979
  Materials from Boxes A (Miscellaneous material, 1921-1972), B (Football programs, 1961-1978), and C (Stanford Sports, circa 1961) were put in the 4-digit section.
  - Letters of recommendation for students and others, A-K, 1951-1971 (Box 1)
  - Letters of recommendation for students and others, L-Z, 1951-1971 (Box 2)
  - Activities Inaugurated, 1946-1968 (Box 3)
    Institute of World Affairs; Institute of International Relations; Speeches given; U.N. Secretary Summer Intern Program; World Affairs Council, Japanese Peace Settlement; Commonwealth Club, Japanese Peace Settlment; Northern California Political Science Association; American Studies Seminar.
  - Activities Inaugurated, 1915?-1969 (Box 4)
    PS 400 Incident; Goheen Committee; Watkins Department Chairmanship; Reiligion at Stanford; In Pont summer conference; Woodrow Wilson Fellowship Committee (State); Political Science Building (20), plans; Stanford Today, Tomorrow; Liquor on Campus; Sobley Affair; Danforth fellowship; Mark X (Mark X plus P)
  - Activities Inaugurated, 1959-1965 (Box 5)
    Stanford Alumni Conferences; Committee on Financial Awards (external); Chaparral incident; Black Reports on Stanford Grading; PACE; ASSU Constitutional Revision; Student Affairs Committee; Bunzel incident; Rothburn group; (PA) Mayor's Charter Review Committee.
  - Activities Inaugurated, 1966-1973 (Box 6)
    Watkins Political (?); Fulbright committee (State); ROTC; Political science department, 50th anniversary celebration; Oscar Nelson lighting recommendation; Lyman inaugural dinner; Political science department, Watkins retirement dinner; Conservative persuasion.
  - Personal folders, A-M, Undated (Box 7)
  - Personal folders, N-Z, Undated (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous course materials, 1946-1953 (Box 9)
    Miscellaneous studies in constitutional development of the UN, eight volumes
  - Work with fraternities, 1939-1978 (Box 10)
    Phi Delta Theta; Fraternities; IFC; Rush; Sigma Nu; Miscellaneous houses.
  - Personal correspondence, A-F, Undated (Box 11)
  - Personal correspondence, G-O, Undated (Box 12)
  - Personal correspondence, P-Z, Undated (Box 13)
  - Publications, 1940 (Box 14)
  - Course material, 1968 and undated (Box 15)
    Political science 500, Teaching; Political science 232, International relations theory; Political science 124, Government of Japan; Political science 135-145, International relations; Political science 132, Principles/problems in US foreign policy; Political science 147/137, UN and antecedents; Class seating charts to 1968; Class interview sign up sheets and interview notes
  - Public notices, Undated (Box 16)
    Comments and compliments received and given; albums
  - Miscellaneous, Undated (Box 17)
    Watkins activities (to be added to activities boxes); grade books
  - Notes, minutes, reports, Undated (Box 18)
  - Publications (mostly Stanford University), Pi Sigma Alpha correspondence files and minute book, Undated (Box 19)
  - Stanford University football programs, 1961-1978 (Box 20)
  - Material (clippings, press releases, some publications, etc) on Stanford University sports, 1961-1979 (Box 21)
  - One folder on Honor Code: clippings articles, brochures; one statistical report "Summary of Honor Code Cases", 1954-1960 (Box 22)